Guide to the Records of the Dean of Women, Washington Square College, Dorothy McSparran Arnold RG.19.3
New York University Archives
Records of the Dean of Women, Washington Square College, Dorothy McSparran Arnold
1924-1967
New York University Archives
Arnold, Dorothy (Dorothy McSparran Arnold)
RG.19.3
2.5 Linear Feet in 5 manuscript boxes
Dorothy McSparran Arnold was Advisor to Women's Office (1924-28), Assistant Dean of Washington Square College (1928-48), and Dean of Women (1948-61) at New York University (NYU). Arnold was the administrator responsible for women's interests at Washington Square College for 43 years. The collection includes her administrative files with minutes, correspondence, memoranda, printed material, news clippings that describe, and photographs that illustrate her activities on behalf of women students.
Related Material at the New York University Archives
Records of the Washington Square Counselor to Women Students (Berger) RG.19.4
Records of the Office of the Chancellor (Elmer Ellsworth Brown) RG.3.0.4
Munn-Recht, Aristine (1st Dean of Women)
The Student Affairs Collection
Women at NYU - Archives H
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
Scope and Content Note
The Dorothy McSparran Arnold Papers describe the evolution of the counseling and programming system Washington Square College developed to coordinate students' intellectual growth with their development as social and moral beings. The papers also reveal the growth of strong women's organizations at the college and present some insights into the attitudes toward women and their roles. Washington Square College, set in an urban environment with a large commuter student body, valued and promoted the extracurricular customs of undergraduate life. Societies and sororities, athletics, undergraduate class loyalties and clubs were community builders. Student activities created the illusion of a society in miniature, preparing the student for citizenship and building loyalty and friendships at the college.
As the College grew in size, the Dean's Office became formally responsible for assuring the academic and personal advisory roles faculty had handled. These responsibilities were gradually divided. The academic counseling, remaining under the authority of the Dean's office was assigned to teaching faculty. The 'official' social and personal counseling became the preserve of faculty (and later student affairs specialists) removed from active teaching. Student activities and counseling became the business of the administration rather than the faculty. Dorothy Arnold switched from teaching to student affairs administrator in 1924, and her career spanned the next 43 years.
The papers have rich material on women's organizations at the College. The League of Women and the Eclectic Society records cover more than thirty years (1920's-50's), giving early organizational information on the group's activities, membership and selection. The Junior Advisory Committee and Faculty Advisory Corps records offer a view of the college's academic and peer counseling programs. There is limited material on fraternity/sorority relations and freshman orientation in the thirties and fifties. Information on the decline of women's athletics is in several folders of the Faculty Advisory Board (1929-1958).
Records of the Student Committee on Educational Policy (1947-59) indicate the shift to give students a more important role in college governance. An important theme throughout the papers is the constant fight Dean Arnold waged for money for adequate facilities and programs for women. The annual reports, the building office file, and the athletic files reveal the struggle. Mrs. Arnold's interest in linking college women to national organizations and interests appear in the American Association of University Women and Mortar Board files.
Biographical Note
Dorothy McSparran Arnold received a B.A. from Cornell University in 1918. She was a professor and administrator at Washington Square College for 43 years. Arriving in 1924 as a young instructor in the English department, Arnold found a ten-year old college with a strong commitment to women's undergraduate education. A year after her arrival she became involved in the development of students' social and moral character. She went into student affairs. During the 1925-26 school year, Arnold began her work as a counselor and administrator for women students at Washington Square College. She was named chairman of the faculty committee on women's interests and, as the catalog for that year states, "Matters affecting the interests of girls in the college should be referred to Mrs. Arnold."
Her activities ranged over all aspects of student life. The next year she became the official Advisor to Women. In December of 1928, the Council appointed her Assistant Dean, recognizing her as an administrator. She received her academic promotion to Assistant Professor in 1926.
She continued as an Assistant Dean until November of 1948, when she became Dean of Women. She reported directly to the Dean of Washington Square College and oversaw women students' physical, social and moral well-being. She served as Dean until her retirement in 1961. As Advisor and Dean, Mrs. Arnold was concerned with promoting the welfare of women students. She worked with students, providing continuity, structure and development of new programs for women. In addition to extensive personal counseling, she served as advisor to most of the campus' women's organizations. Her office organized or coordinated many activities of the League of Women, women's honorary and social societies and women's athletics. She also helped to develop a peer counseling program to aid freshwomen and transfer students' adjustment to college life. The Junior Advisors Committee, under her direction, was an important resource for newcomers and a place to recognize outstanding junior women. The League of Women, the Eclectic honorary society and Pan-Hellenic Council were other vehicles for recognizing and developing women student leaders.
As an administrator Dorothy Arnold worked for women students, providing representation on college committees directly concerned with student issues. She was a member of the Faculty Advisory Committee for Women's Athletics, Faculty Committee on fraternities and sororities connected with the Student Committee on Educational Policy, various scholarship committees and the committee on faculty-student advising. She was also an advisor on disciplinary, and financial aid matters. As a Dean she participated on college and university governance committees, the Cabinet of the College, Advisement Council, and the Council of Deans.
Dean Dorothy McSparran Arnold died on November 22, 1971.
Access Restrictions
Administrative records and unpublished reports of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation. Access to files spanning multiple years will be opened to researchers based on the date of the most recent materials. Board of Trustees records are closed for 35 years from the date of creation. Materials related to personnel, grievances, job and fellowship searches and applications, and all files that fall under the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) are permanently restricted. Additional restrictions may apply to other materials in this collection. For questions regarding specific restrictions, please contact the University Archives.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Dean of Washington Square and University College, New York University.
Clippings (information artifacts); Minutes (administrative records); Memorandums.; Correspondence.; New York (N.Y.).; Photographs.; Women's rights.; Washington Square College. Women's Office; Washington Square College. Student Committee on Educational Policy; Washington Square College. League of Women; Washington Square College. Eclectic Society; Gamma Gamma Sigma (Association of Women Students); Bradley, Lyman R.; Burgum, Edwin Berry, 1894-; Berger, Dorothea; New York University
- Advisement Council, correspondence., 1937-1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Advisement Council, minutes, 1945-1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Advisement Council, minutes, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Advisement Council, minutes, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Advisement Council, minutes, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Advisement Council, minutes, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Advisement Council, minutes, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Advisement Council, minutes, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Advisement Council, minutes, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Advisory Corps (Faculty), correspondence., 1953-1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Advisory Corps (Faculty), minutes, 1950, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Alumnae Club, report, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Alumni Christmas Parties, correspondence, 1938-1942, 1945-1949 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Alumni Christmas Parties, correspondence, 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Alumni Christmas Parties, correspondence, 1956-1960 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Alumni Federation, announcements, 1958, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Alumni Saturday, correspondence, 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- American Association of University Women, correspondence, 1927-1929 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- A.A.U.W. (See Above) correspondence, 1934-1936 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- A.A.U.W., correspondence, 1953-1955, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- American Red Cross, Blood Bank, correspondence, 1941-1945 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- American Red Cross, Blood Bank, 1950, 1953-1960 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Annual Reports to the Dean, 1934-1935, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Art Competition at Washington Square, correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Faculty Advisory Committee for Women's Athletics, Minutes, rules, plans, 1929-1930 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  General note
  Also called Board of Control for Women's Athletics
- Faculty Advisory Committee for Women's Athletics, correspondence, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Faculty Advisory Committee for Women's Athletics, minutes, correspondence, 1938-1944 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Name changes to "University Board of Athletic Control for Women's Athletics," Dec. 1938.
- Faculty Advisory Committee for, Women's Athletics, minutes, correspondence, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Faculty Advisory Committee for Women's Athletics, minutes, correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Faculty Advisory Committee for Women's Athletics, minutes, correspondence, 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Faculty Advisory Committee for Women's Athletics, minutes, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Faculty Advisory Committee for Women's - Athletics, 1956, minutes, correspondence, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- B - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1950-1957 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Bradley, Lyman R.; report, printed material, (see also clipping file), 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Building Office, correspondence, memos., 1950-1955, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Burgam, Edwin Berry; printed material, reports, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Cabinet of the College (Washington Square), 1928, 1930-1932 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Cabinet of the College (Washington Square), Minutes, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Council of Deans (All-University), Minutes, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Eclectic Society, Membership List, Constitution, Report, Minutes, 1922, 1935-1936, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Eclectic Society, Minutes, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Eclectic Society, Eligibility lists, membership, correspondence, 1947, 1950-1955 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Eclectic Society, Eligibility list, selection materials, correspondence, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Eclectic Society Dinners, correspondence, 1954-1957 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Eclectic Society, point system, 1940-1949 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Eclectic Society Survey of Extracurricular Activities, 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
- Faculty Committee on Sororities and Fraternities, 1935-1937 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Fraternity and Sorority Status, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Freshman orientation: printed materials, 1944, 1946, 1948-1958 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Freshman orientation: advising, 1936, 1938, 1948-1951, 1954, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Junior Advisory Committee, 1933-1939, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Junior Advisory Committee, 1946, 1948-1949 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Junior Advisory Committee, 1951-1955 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Junior Advisory Committee, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- RESTRICTED - Junior Advisory Committee, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Junior Advisory Committee, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- RESTRICTED - Junior Advisory Committee, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Junior Advisory Committee, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Junior Advisory Committee, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Junior Advisory Committee, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- League of Women, 1933-1937 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- League of Women, 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- RESTRICTED - League of Women, 1947-1951 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- League of Women, 1947-1951 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- League of Women, 1954-1958 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- League of Women: handbooks, bank book, Constitution, 1924-1925, 1926-1927 (Box 3, File 20)
- League of Women: programs, ca. 1950-1959 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- League of Women: minutes and correspondence, ca. 1922-1928 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- League of Women: minutes and correspondence, 1929-1931 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- League of Women: scholarships, 1928-1936 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- RESTRICTED - League of Women, 1922-1928 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Loeb Student Center, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Dean Loomis, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Lounges, 1925-1943 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Mortar Board, 1927-1928 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Mortar Board, 1933-1934, 1936, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Parents' receptions, 1955-1957 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Parents' receptions, 1958-1960 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Phi Beta Kappa, 1927, 1932, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Phi Beta Kappa: Constitution, rituals, minutes, bulletin, 1928, 1933, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Scholarships, Washington Square College, 1926, 1929-1931, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Use of Student Activities room 214, 1937, 1944-1949, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- RESTRICTED - Student Committee on Educational Policy, 1947-1952 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Student Committee on Educational Policy, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Reports of Student Committee on Educational Policy, 1959, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- RESTRICTED - Student Committee on Educational Policy: selection of undergraduate members, 1947, 1955-1959, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Student press conference, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Clippings: NYU campus, 1946-1948, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Clippings: Colleges, 1948-1951 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Clippings: NYU faculty and administration, 1946, 1948-1949, 1951-1953, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Clippings: Dean Arnold, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Clippings: Co-ed cheerleaders, 1949-1950 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Clippings: Eclectic, 1935. 1942, 1945-1946, 1948-1949, 1953; 1945-1949 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Clippings: League of Women, 1948-1949, 1953, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Clippings: Friends, 1945-1947, 1949-1953, 1955-1957 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Clippings: NYU students and alumni, 1947-1955,1957 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Clippings: Phi Beta Kappa, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Clippings: New York University, 1949, 1952-1953, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Clippings: Lounges, 101 and 209 Main, 1940, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Clippings: Student Educational Policy Committee, 1948-1950 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Clippings: Women's athletics, 1942, 1949-1950, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- RESTRICTED - Athletic eligibility, personal files, private files, 1936-1961 (Box 6)
  RESTRICTED MATERIALS